[Music]
our
subject today is is karma right
it is karma and forgiveness and
forgiveness yeah
we've talked a lot about uh no mythology
and we talked about the eternal return
of the same
like everything is circular and comes
back to the same place
over and over again now this was the
shared world view by
anybody until like three to four
thousand years ago
eventology came along and limitology
essentially the idea that
no it's not exactly the same thing that
returns
there's a small difference with each
loop
and that small difference is
say accumulated information so you store
information outside of your own brain
and suddenly you write things down and
the next generation can then inherit
more information than you ever had
and that idea of course is maybe one of
only two or three major ideas
humans ever come up with was a raster's
idea 3700 years ago
and that's the beginning of entology now
what's also interesting with that
is that this enables something that
didn't happen before
existed for it's called forgiveness and
we talked a lot about lynch mobs in the
past and
we all three met in denmark this last
week and we talked about
that the current lynch mobs we're seeing
everywhere right now are pagan
all right see if they're pagan that
means they're probably also prevalent in
the east
because hinduism is still a pagan
religion so
uh and certainly there's a lot of
paganism going on in china so we have a
problem here with chinese and indian
culture we have a problem with our own
heritage that's popping up again
we're not even christian any longer we
go back to paganism so we need we need
a good definition of what you mean by
karma and what you mean by forgiveness
like what is it
notion of karma and then we have there
is a more sophisticated version of that
i think perhaps the same is true okay
let's not allow
karma to escape the cheap way here let's
confront karma with all the problems
that inherent in paganism it's okay so
karma originally is a pagan concept and
it is that anything you do
it will undoubtedly follow you until the
day you die and possibly into your next
life
that's why it's also tied to
reincarnation because everything returns
to the same means you might also be
reborn
so reincarnation and karma are tied
together they're very pagan concepts
and essentially this is what the lynch
bob is after the lynch mob when it's
attacking you if you're the scapegoat
the lynchburg will tell you that there
is no forgiveness
there's no way out of your sins or out
of your shame you must die
yeah so it's total pre-pre-destination
and that
is a vulgar notion of karma from my
point of view
i don't say it's a vulgar notion i think
that's what karma is if you want to
elaborate on that later yeah i would
allow you to it's a problem
because i would love to say buddhism
from this if we can that's basically the
theme for this conversation
so um the problem is that though that
what soraster then discovers and this is
the original sense of forgiveness the
seration sense is that oh wait a second
if there's difference with each
repetition that means it's actually
great for say a youngster
to be able to do something and then make
a mistake and learn from the mistake and
then do it again
this is essentially how life works i
mean life cannot work without
memory without memory inside the cell
there's no point to life at all
so memories as early as a cell becomes a
life form
so there's always some kind of memory
because you will memorize your previous
experience this is what it would say
and through this experience you would
then you have a memory also learn so you
don't repeat your mistakes
so the zoroastrian sense of forgiveness
is very simple and very ethical this is
problems or rasterism think it solves
the lynch model problem
because essentially say no no no wait a
second there is no eternal con
damnation there is no sin or shame in
that sense
because actually you can be forgiven for
your acts
not your sins you'll be forgiven for
your act if you have failed
and this is actually the sore astral
notion of forgiveness is the very simple
one you do when you do entrepreneurship
it is
oh you failed try again and if you
failed again
try again that is forgiveness the
zoroastrians it's strictly ethical
imperative nothing else but the problem
is that
both this does not exist in paganism
because everything returns the same
means there is no forgiveness there's no
way out
if you do something it's eternally valid
there's no way out of karma basically
yeah that is original karma
the problem though is to me is the
abrahamic religions of which erasticism
is not a part
the abrahamic religions we do this and
christianity and islam also have the
different versions of forgiveness i
think judaism is the most sophisticated
one
john kippur is a perfect example of that
but in christianity there's also
forgiveness but it's
loving and caring it's called mercy but
the problem is
in those religions you have a perfect
god and if you have a state of
perfection that you relate to
you end up with actually what the
muslims eventually do with a tub or
whatever it's called table and gothi
but the different concepts within islam
of forgiveness so basically is that
you made a terrible mistake you must go
to god and ask for mercy and never ever
do it again
but there's no learning experience
involved in that sense of forgiveness
this is my problem with the abrahamic
forgivenesses so we have a problem on
one end which is the karma vulgar carmia
called it
which then generates pagan lynch mobs
the other problem is a forgiveness
that comes at a point of mercy from an
omnipotent omniscient perfect god
but zeratism doesn't have perfection it
doesn't have a perfect god at all it has
forever changed that's exactly why i
think that is the forgiveness i want to
work from
how does this relate to buddhism i've
got a few like comments about that like
i i think the point of
buddhism basically uh is is
is to kind of transcend karma for one
thing
so so it it's it's uh the whole point of
buddhis so it's a bit like
grace or something like that when you
transcend karma
um the whole point is that you're not
uh bound to the past um and
and that there's there's a there's a way
there's a way to to go beyond karma and
that there's an open future in some
sense
like there's there's this creative open
future
so that that would that's what i would
say is a more
but how does forgiveness relate to that
i mean who forgives him
who forgives whom well the forgiveness
is is probably
i would say it's like the the awareness
of the karmic knot is what breaks the
karmic knot
in some sense so that's why buddhists
meditate and and you know try to break
through this karmic knot
to to experience um
i find that dissatisfying what does
thomas say
yeah mr experience of buddhism in
relation to
unforgiving and the forgiving well the
first thing that comes to mind when i
hear you that is that um
maybe we need to be a bit precise about
what what paganism means here
i mean paganism has a very precise
definition or
it's a very precise concept in in uh in
the
in the girardian context right i mean
it's it's
it's i mean it's the old story right so
there's conflict in the community you
find the scapegoat you kill the
scapegoat
that way you pacify the community and
you deify the scapegoat
now so so that's that's basically the
essence of paganism right and you said
something about
like hinduism and uh and china that that
had a lot of paganism
so i'd like to i'd like you to unpack
that a bit
okay i should maybe call it nomidology
so
a normalology without eventology is all
we had
as long as it could only memorize in our
own heads but then the question is
in normatology if you so let's say if
you have a culture that that puts the
emphasis on normatology is that
automatically a pagan culture
it is pagan in this sense it's pagan in
the sense that karma cannot be forgiven
because there's no
authority to forgive it that's exactly
why i believe
that's when you create a lynch mob and
remove
your karma and put it on somebody else
you can clean yourself
why do you need an authority to to
forgive karma
well you're responsible to somebody if
you act
you're in the tribe your actions have
repercussions to the tribe's interests
i actually i would interpret this karma
more in the sense of like in the
nietzschean sense that you you have to
go beyond being the man of the hurt
you know the the tasman that you all
that you all also uh
touched upon in previous podcasts the
unobject that you have to go beyond that
because that's irma right the karma is
basically just while you're
you're you're thrown into this society
that has this
this generalized opinion and you can
just you can just follow that
and then you can kind of see that as a
certain karma right
yeah well there's yeah there's different
levels of karma like karma just means
action right that's the literal meaning
of it
so so there's all you're born into this
world of karmas
right there's there's your personal
karmas and your family karmas
and your national karmas and well andrew
have you used that i mean
i don't know i mean this is a kind of an
aspect of buddhism that's
somehow kind of you know well i was yeah
i was looking at
you know trump who often has a radical
you know shift on things but you know
the vajra is is a thing that it breaks
karma it just cuts through karma
right so that you can experience the now
sort of thing and so that you're free of
of of you know past
burdens and you're you're you're
um you're free to act in a sense so so
that's his inter that's his
interpretation of karma which is perhaps
we could say there's a hinayana version
of karma
right or there's a sutrianic version of
karma which is just like do good things
do good actions right make you know good
actions to have good results and
that's the kind of like very simplistic
if not very interesting
yeah version of karma that's maybe
that's the nominal ideology he's talking
about there's no way out of it right
yeah you just have to keep doing good
good things and be a good boy and uh
yeah but that's that's cheap shooting
that's what happens if you do a bad act
that's what's interesting where is the
forgiveness part of this the fact
you should do good acts you're
recommended to do good acts yeah that's
that's a
that's a truism in any culture right but
here the question is what if you do the
bad act and what kind of bad act is it
there's intentionally bad acts obviously
there are just well let's say you're a
murderer right you're a murderer
can can you go beyond the karma of being
a murderer and
again again the person can have
forgiveness right no the different
reasons why the stories are
no no wait a second the different
reasons why you're a murderer you can be
a warrior you can
legally kill someone no i mean like a
crime if you commit a terrible you know
heinous crime and and murder a family
according to its standards so that was
and he practiced all this black magic
and he was very into paganism right
and he met as his teacher and his
teacher said build these
you know build these towers continually
build these towers and then
and then and then smash them down again
and and he became free of of the karma
of his
his negative acts and he was forgiven
you know not forgiven by
by his teacher but but existentially he
was free
this gets weird but okay i want to go
back to the social aspect of this
because i think we need to return to the
lynch small because that's where we
started this conversation
like several episodes ago so my promise
is that if you move
we realize we have a problem here it's
called karma it's universally a problem
your acts will haunt you
whether you like it or not and and
culturally they do
in a non-biological society which was
any society to this planet for say the
last hundred thousand years
until very recently that was a given you
know bad acts had repercussions the only
way to not a bad ex was to basically say
bad acts are completely unacceptable
there was a zero tolerance toward bad
acts that's essentially what
you know deep karma would be i'm gonna
object again i'm sorry like
yeah you like uh in the odyssey all kind
of the gods do all kinds of bad acts and
they get away with it and
you're way later in history your way the
odyssey you're way
you're way beyond this is no matter
logical and the tolerance already
happened
as soon as you have written literature
you can't see there's no ethics in those
early stories right
they're not early stories they're recent
stories we're talking about hundreds of
thousands of years here okay anyway go
on go on
okay i found a little bit more whereas
social biological reshape was a
dissociate the associate lasted for 60
to 70 thousand years the artist is way
after that
you can't use written literature here to
make another gods the whole thing that
that
thomas is talking about the the pagan
lynch mobs and and the
that's later that's later again that's
after nominology that's after
okay exclusive numerology followed by a
number of the plus avatars
absolutely i mean that's at the
beginning that's how we became humans
no wait a second this is a continual
argument we always have actually
zoroaster is a thousand years before the
odyssey
so raster knows already then that
eventology is a fact
so no the greeks were immersed well the
egyptians
were talking about a world where people
believe in gods and wrath you know god's
is all about forefathers it's ur mothers
and ur fathers it's not about gods even
yet
the chinese never even went for the gods
so wait a second
my pointer is this it's about the lynch
it's about the mob it's about society
you got to get
rid of this excess there's an excess
hair or bad acts
some of you got to solve that and of
course the way to do that in a gerardian
way is basically to put the blame on a
scapegoat take anybody who won't protest
make that person the scapegoat and drag
them through the streets and kill them
and you get the release
so there's not only envy which gerard is
correct about
there's also a release in terms of the
karmas being put on this creature
so in christianity christ on the cross
does both
both throw all the sins on to him but at
the same time obviously
he's an example of what happens if you
scapegoat somebody so we should avoid
scapegoating
you can argue both and it's brilliant
with christianity i don't have a problem
christ takes on the escape i think
christianity christianity's strongest
point
is his forgiveness but i want to argue
here i started with michael butler last
week in denmark
i want to argue here the christian sense
of forgiveness and surah sense of
forgiveness and probably jewish in
between
are different and they're all rich these
traditions are rich because they try to
deal with how to avoid the lynch mob
what soresters basically do is they say
okay
bad activity was intentional major
problem but at least a non-intentional
bad act
is not drug drug is all about intentions
evil is all about intelligence or
astronomy
it's an ethical principle without
moralism so basically that's why so
rasters are great entrepreneurs
that's one of the wealthiest people ever
known on this planet the parsons of
india is the wealthiest ethnic minority
ever invented right they send their kids
to school they get great degree
great degrees and they go out and
conquer the world now how do you become
such a successful culture
if you don't have a principle it's
actually very clever that principle is
that oh you made a mistake
listen try again that is original
forgiveness to me if you go back about 4
000 years because of eventology
i would argue that it's impossible
unless the event happens and the event
is neutral
the event can be ecstatic or it can be
traumatic
it's just difference and you can prepare
for that so that means
when you when you notice that there's a
difference with each repetition
you start to plan for the next
repetition that's what civilization is
you start a plan for okay it's gonna
we're gonna go for another loop now of
the eternal recurrence of the same
let's make the deviations something more
productive this time rather than
destructive this is
asha versus druid
i let the repetition happen the
difference that come out can be anything
usually it's traumatic usually terrible
right
because nature will go towards the
terrible the traumatic unless you try to
direct it
towards the event big static okay so you
go towards ecstatically you create an
authentic event this is alan badu by the
way this is all phallic philosophy it's
easy
i don't believe being an event returns
to this idea you can't direct the future
by planning for it towards the more
constructive
that's asha now in that process you
discover and by the way if we do go
towards a traumatic
we intended to go towards the
constructed
grade okay can we learn from that yes we
can
because we're a life form that has
memory we can actually store that
information we can write it in the books
that's you start writing bibles you
write the book of job write cain and
abel you write all these stories
this is what happens if you do wrong so
by reading the story
you can avoid making that mistake so
there's some link to
literacy and forgiveness yes okay
thank you that's interesting rasterism
and judaism are children of that and
then christianity takes on a more
sentimental version of that
which i think nietzsche properly
criticizes
because he finds it meek and weak
because the forgiveness in christianity
osama becomes too generous
or too sentimental and i think the
problem nietzsche hasn't really found
out is that the more
perfect you make god who's the authority
gives the forgiveness
the more perfect god is the more you
venture resort into the trap or islam
ended up and islam there is no
forgiveness there's only repentance
well i have something to say about that
in terms of the the jewish tradition
because in certain aspects of the jewish
tradition god has a dark side it's
called the siddhatra or something like
that like
god is not only good and pure
and absolute it's there's also a dark
side to god
and so he a human being's job is
actually to help god
that's just part of the the this part of
the jewish um um
um you know so so we're more implied
we're more
we have more of a purpose here rather
than let's say up you know a
protestant idea where where you know
you're just sort of you know you just
sort of
uh uh there's just this predestination
you're just sort of bound to karma
love it so so in judaism in judaism you
do these acts uh they're called misfus
right
in order to help god because god's
really bored if
human beings are not there to to help in
this creative act so so
so it stands for giving not a beautiful
wait a second is that forgiveness in
judaism a social event or is it a divine
event
it doesn't really matter sure i don't
know i know much about how they
how they what they do for forgiveness
okay what's important here though is
that you just describe the concept of
god which is imperfection
and there's no perfection at all it's
invented by the greeks way later so
the aura and master are split phallus
that in itself says it's not infinite
it's a finite entity and definite entity
is not perfect because nothing is ever
perfect because the world is ever
changing
fresh or correct so that's the point so
zoroastrian i think is gets away with
this
and it's a question we brought up before
is that why did the sore astron empires
not have tons of lynch mobs they were
apparently incredibly rare in the
persian empire
incredibly rare and sore probably
because they had a way of dealing with
karma i would say like a correct way
of dealing with karma that's how you
prevent the lynch mods right no
no well wait partly yes but
you've got to have a culture a proper
cultural forgiveness but the forgiveness
must not be sentimental and
devoid of reality it must be related to
something real
yeah now the question i returned to then
is that how is buddhism throughout
history tried to solve this because i
think it has to do with the buddhist
attitude towards the lynch mob
because as long as the lynch as long as
you've got karma out there
and karma is a fiendishly hard thing to
get rid of and you can only do it on a
personal level but not on the social
level
i see the lynch mobs are still there in
the streets i don't see how you actually
get out of the lynch mob culture unless
you
have a social function that forgives the
sinner
or you know forgives you not repentance
but properly forgives you
so you can try again because if you
allow people to try again you can't kill
them
the whole idea of the death penalty
disappears in a culture
where you're allowed to change your ways
and you can be forgiven for your past
what do you think thomas do you want to
do to refund that
the classic way to avoid uh to avoid
mobs to avoid scapegoating is is
prohibition
religious prohibition so that you avoid
too much
envy and jealousy because that's what
leads to mobs
so that's why that's why all religions
have very very
severe prohibitions with respect to
sexual sexuality because sexuality is
the
is an extreme source of envy and
jealousy so that's why
what for example christians get very
wrong right so they think that there's
something inherently problematic with
sexuality
there isn't anything probably inherently
problematic with sexuality
it's just that it very easily leads to
jealousy and
envy and that's why you need to be
careful with it yeah
well i i lived in a buddhist monastery
and and
there are confession rituals you know
you you confess your
your you confess your karma i guess
to other people it could be your
thoughts could be similar to i guess
christianity there's a
there's a kind of confession process but
the confession is followed by the
blessing
uh in christianity you're you're you're
from your sins off you go
do you do that with the book you do that
do you do that within buddhism did you
practice that in buddhism or is it just
a you know you let your heart out you
pour your heart out and you tell people
what you've been up to but that's you do
in any 12-step program
yeah 12-step programs do not offer you
forgiveness
um well yeah you're you're you're there
there's
there's the same i don't know i guess
the difference between catholic
confessional is you go and meet somebody
and he
he he he forgives you or something
whereas that forgiveness is the point
not the confession
no i'm back to what thomas just said
though i agree
completely so this is where christianity
runs into problems to me christianity
its problems increasingly come out of
mimicking
previous what i call the major religions
here i would consider christianity in
islam as minor religions and i think
islam has enormous problems because
islam is like
is it it's like the pop culture parody
of of what went before it certainly
relation between zorasis and islam is
clearly that way
the same thing i think with judaism and
christianity there's a richness
into these religions the older they are
and the older they are they come
less out of these sort of platonist
ideas of perfection and infinity and
immortality
because if you get immortality out the
door if you get infinity out the door to
get perfection out the door in a
religion
it's probably really good religion to
work from
you see what i mean it also doesn't then
have a problem with sexuality it
realizes
the problem is envy because i don't see
the jews and i don't see the saurons or
the buddhists having a major problem
with sexuality
i think no they don't christians wrongly
focus on sexuality itself instead of
focusing on
the sexuality is is one of those things
people fight over it's just
therefore therefore their place ended
with sexuality itself
as a source of sin and christianity yeah
yeah well yeah that's that's uh i think
we all agree with that this
um whereas yeah you might go and live in
a monastery and you might
avoid sexuality but you're not you're
not you don't consider it to be
something
evil or what did thomas say
well in the sense that christianity
tries to do the
the right thing but they don't really
it's that they confuse the means with
the
ends right so
regulating christianity is just
regulating sexuality is a means to an
end and that is
to limit the the the proliferation of
envy and jealousy
so in that sense in that sense we
disagree we have the institution of
marriage
and all that inherently problematic
what are you okay can you finish that
thomas i'm sorry i interpreted yeah
that's in this sense i mean as much as i
like paglia but there we kind of
disagree with pacquiao
because she kind of says that that
sexuality is inherently catonic
but it's inherently problematic it
doesn't really have to be like that
uh-huh yeah yeah
okay that's where you go utopian thomas
this gets interesting this is a whole
new direction for tonight's conversation
but i love it well paglia says art is
sort of like you know wait wait a second
question is good
and under andre i love your talk in this
case i'd love thomas to elaborate more
on the difference between hammurich and
paglia when it comes to sexuality
as such
[Music]
i think i got it but yeah it's something
that i i read also there was a book
about
uh gerard's theory and uh there was
somebody who wrote who wrote something
about the view of camille paglia and
that
paglia kind of ceased
maybe i'm remembering this not correctly
but basically the
the idea is that the sexuality is in
inherently problematic as
as a problematic thing but you can you
can but
if you look at it from from the point of
view of why is it problematic well it's
not inherently problematic but it's just
because
it's it's one of those things that lead
to jealousy and envy and that's the real
problem and jealousy and envy will
come from all kinds of areas so you can
that you can get that from
from material greed you can have that
from prestige and and and stuff like
that so
so in that sense there is so so
christianity has a focus
a big focus on on sexuality that is a
bit um
that makes it a bit unworkable for many
people i think that the views of
of christianity with respect to to to
sexuality is something that
has turned many people away i remember
paglia also saying that the power of the
catholic culture
right is the fact that they repress
sexuality and then so therefore
it it i think this is called this art
and
power and and i think that's totally
wrong that's that was fabulous
that religions religions use sexuality
to gain power
i mean i never really understood that
how would that how would that happen
that's not what they're doing they're
trying to avoid
people to become jealous and envious of
each other
and if they do that you get conflict
throughout the whole community and they
start killing each other
or they start killing scapegoats that's
why you have all these religious
prohibitions
that's also why you try to distribute
wealth within communities in all
religions
the same thing and this is obviously
problematic in the persian empire
because
they got agnostics who said we should
totally even out the wealth
which is of course the master kites the
origin of islam and of socialism in the
west starts with mastoc and his idea
that we should basically have a state
that takes all the property so we can
then distribute it
according to needs right the vulgar
version of marxism is the same thing
when marx for example said that to each
according to his needs
he meant to each according to his needs
considering who's going to work tomorrow
morning
meaning that the workers should have
more than anybody else because they're
going to go to work the next month he
didn't mean
according to body size or anything like
that at all that's vulgar and marxism
one of the problems with the tax marxism
they they don't understand this
but the master creates that problem so
that was inherent problems or asterism
because within an
empire it was really hard to distribute
wealth to the extent you avoided
envy so avoiding mv central to really i
agree on that but
i disagree and actually agree with pogba
here because sexuality is problematic
but problematic here is in a delusion
sense productively problematic
because it's ambivalent and anything
that that dances on ambivalence your own
subjectivity is another example of that
you can never really agree on who you
are who you are you can never really
understand yourself that's the point
according to hegel that is yourself the
selfie status which is concerned with
being yourself and cannot make up its
mind what it is
that is being yourself to begin with
according to hebrew so at the same thing
goes to sexuality subjectivity and
sexuality are very similar here
the same thing goes for the worldview we
can't really agree on how the world
operates because we can't agree or it
operates we'll stare at the stars every
night
and there are you know riddles out on
how the world operates and this
of course where it's origin of science
and curiosities it's like
we can never really nail how the world
works
and and that is ambivalence and i think
sexuality should more be compared to
subjectivity in science
then it should be compared as a moral
problem it's it's
it's the three artistic problem or
something the thrill of it is that it
never reaches a balance and that's what
we want to avoid here
the tallest fantasies of the yin and the
young reach in some kind of balance is
what i'm against i
i think there's always three not two and
the third
force is always the one that starts
everything gets everything moving again
whenever you're close to anything that
looks like a balance
that's why for example contemporary law
concerning sexuality is completely
deranged
there is no such thing as a contractual
consent before you [ __ ] somebody because
the [ __ ] is gonna be terrible
if you do that and that is problematic
right it's um but it's a good problem
like the law said the problems are
fantastic
but it seems that we are i think that
when i hear you talking also about uh
about uh zoryastranism then then it
seems that it's it's all about
it's about skills versus not having
skills
it's about it it's about constructive
action or or action that actually works
and that
that accomplishes something in the in
the world versus
versus clumsiness or ignorance or just
lack of skills
rather than good versus evil oh yeah
they're still good versus evil and
zoroastrianism
remember this is the most misunderstood
concept or religion
ever like anything you've heard about
soras and forget it okay read the
original text go to the invest and you
discover the good and evil didn't even
exist its concepts at the time
the probably egyptian and come much
later no what consists what
what existed osha also meaning how
things work
so why not operate in a way that
actually is aligned with how things work
that means just basically optimize your
thinking optimize your speech
optimize your behavior that is the
principle that
every zoroastrian uses in the meditation
every morning i'm just going to optimize
myself during the day
and and that is also and then the
opposite of that drugs is essentially
oh you couldn't care less and because
you couldn't care less
you go envious of others who've actually
made an effort and that starts a
destructive spiral
that becomes poison within a society
that is the understanding of drugs and i
prefer to use the original terms here
so forgiveness here is essentially i
will not forgive you if you don't
seriously mean you're gonna try again
and learn from your previous experience
that sounds like a bit aristotle who
said it
you know that apparently the romans
mistranslated aristotle
aristotle he didn't mean good and evil
he meant excellence or something or
yeah yeah what do you think where do you
think you got that from
i think i i probably got it from
heidegger but no where do you think
aristotle got that idea from
oh right does his roster yeah okay
so if you study it right miracles
are both court philosophers in the
personal empire i mean the connection
with persian greece is just
embarrassingly underrated right so
there's not this platonic good and evil
it's more of a it's more of a pragmatic
um you know idea yeah and actually you
and i under have a conversation with
john for varkid that he reminded me
that i cannot put new platinus and under
the same umbrella as i do with platonism
because with neoplatonism coming out of
alexandria in egypt the influence from
the persons had returned and it was a
modest
understanding of the world is actually
acceptable very important gets really
interesting you start studying him
and that again is that the influence
goes back and forth in the hellenistic
world
so so that happens all the time okay
february has a problem with that i think
it's fantastic i think the hellenistic
world was fantastic
but it's it's the cross cross breeding
of these ideas
that that actually were still working
with today
makes sense so how about the christian
forgiveness here nietzsche
i want to go back to forgetting
forgiveness because i don't think we've
gotten to the bottom of
no let's go to the christian version
here because it it
no matter i think it's the best thing
christianity gave to the world and i
think it has
paid off handsomely in the west for the
last two thousand years been incredible
i mean
we couldn't have limited companies in in
in the corporate world unless i said
christianity had forgiveness
implemented into it and you went for a
confession you confessed
you took it all out and actually i think
forgiveness in christianity because you
also forgive your brother
your sister in the congregation is a way
of getting rid of a load it's just like
either you have to carry this heavy
weight around that
actually somebody did something nasty to
you or you you you were involved in
somebody who did something nasty they
shouldn't have done or whatever
you want to have it undone and the way
to have it undone is to learn how to
forgive
yeah but it avoids the escalation
reciprocal escalation
because if somebody did you wrong okay
you react by
giving that person the same thing and
then that person
again reacts and then so you have that's
the typical escalation so
that that leads to mobs and that needs
scapegoating so
christianity very much tries to to
defuse that mechanism through
forgiveness
yeah and it took until the the end of
the 19th
century or something before it stopped
in the balkans right and there was again
a pagan heritage
it's just like somebody killed in this
village would go into the next village
and kill one of theirs then they come
back here and kill us and it goes on
forever
it's exactly these escalations that you
try to avoid and and
i think it comes out of a more imperial
understanding of humanity so it's like
okay
we can't have violence here in this
province where people just go around and
kill each other all the time
so we take all the young men out of
there put them in an army somewhere and
invade
uh and then we teach them a religion
where you just don't do that and there's
a way out
and that's why you put a confession
booth in the church rebuilt here
so it's not just a ritual place where
you repeat the same thing
over and over again with the
nomadological approach to reality it's
just
repetition of the same over and over
again the same rituals
with the same ending and this is where i
think the pagan lynch mobs come in and
and the cleansing of the community by
putting you know all the karma on to
one body and then get rid of that body
and somehow you're cleansed for the next
year or so
yeah and then of course you have to
repeat it all over again the next year
that was the problem with that model
when we had growing populations and we
became
settled and we started storing
information
this just got more and more destructive
and worse and worse and there was
there had to be a way out of it and and
so raster presented one version of it
obviously there are other ways of trying
to deal with that i think all the major
religions do
deal with that they deal with how are we
going to distribute wealth
and create less source of envy
and just avoid envy because it causes so
much destruction
cain and abel is the oldest book in the
old testament for a good reason
this is what happens this is what
happened you go and kill your brother
because you end them just on envy how do
you avoid enemy well
it's both your own personal journeys to
avoid envy
but also we need to create a community
where this just won't happen there's
also the notion of loving the stranger
which you've brought up a few times
like the samaritan who lifts the the the
guy from the the ditch or whatever who's
not a part of his tribe
he kind of um he breaks that that
pattern as
well like uh yeah but it's a rastiness
in the way you solve it that you
tolerate other religions
you basically the different fields the
different levels
so you have one level eva was saying
that that this was very problematic
actually like
this was a problematic notion of of
christianity
when it when it became uh sort of
institutionalized
institutionalized we can return to that
but let me just go back to our
assistance this is older right
what they do is that you have one level
which you call abstract religion
abstract religion is the religion of the
priests and the military and all those
guys in the specific
and it's often abstract in the sense you
can worship a completely
uh ignorant god it doesn't care about us
you know whatever
you know if that's the truth that's the
truth you just go and search
for the truth mysterian cults always did
that right the occult always did that
they went beyond the bard absolute to do
that and they made that pursuit and it
wasn't meant for the public
that's why those religions were never
written down but that
created two different fields but the
other one was folk religion which we
call iconology so you go to the lesser
gods and you worship your eldest presti
or ganesha or whatever
you can relate to them because you can
talk to them like an older brother or
or or or a father figure or a mother
figure or something like that
in christianity that's praying to the
virgin mary so she can talk to god
right so or the saints
those are the lesser gods and and that's
why you have two different levels of the
religion and therefore you can have
tolerance
and if you can have tolerance hey you
can love the stranger he doesn't have to
share your faith
your faith is not on your forehead
you're just running to each other in the
city
you live in your blocks your quarters
with your religion
he lives in his block over there with
his religion and all the major trade
cities along the trade routes were
constructed like that
from xi'an in china all the way to cairo
that all these
jewish quarters and persian quarters and
whatever afghan quarters in turkish
quarters
where minorities lived and they
practiced a different religion it was
completely accepted
it was he was even endorsed right so
i think loving a stranger actually
starts with creating
a container with within which you can do
that christianity and this makes it a
moral imperative
i think if you're pagan you can't love
the stranger right because you're
completely bound to your tribe right you
of course yes so you're not gonna help
the guy out of the ditch who's not like
you you're you're
you know you can only surround yourself
with people who are
well if you don't understand yourself
that's necessary
there's no there's no space from your
levels from
is where can you find food to eat you
run into another tribe you kill them
i mean it was it was constant warfare
because anybody from a different tribe
than yours you would kill them
yes that's how he lived as long as we
were nomadic
population was never more than 3 million
on the entire planet
but the roman empire was was very we had
a lot of different cultures a lot of
different religions and it was utterly
pagan so
i think that you you can have pagan
making societies of pagan religions that
that can deal with a stranger
but it just comes at the cost of
regularly killing scapegoats
yeah but the roman empire the roman
empire inherited a structure from the
persians
the persians were about 600 years before
the roman empire so yeah
they mimicked each other yeah but pagan
religion works fine right i mean
it's not as if it doesn't work i mean
this thing works very well is this very
brutal i mean because
you know because you regularly are going
to kill people that's
that's built into the religion so
instead of letting the victimh
mechanism run rampant you're going to
organize it that's what what the nazis
tried to do right
the nazis tried to bring back organized
paganism
yeah right yeah and so and then
basically you know it could have worked
because
the roman empire was also organized
paganism they just killed a lot of
people
you know like if you want to pacify the
the the community if you have problems
in the community
then you just kill people and and they
made that work for a long time so it's
not impossible to make it work it's just
that
at some point you know uh christianity
kind of came up with the idea that
there's something better and i guess
zoroastrianism also did that that you
can organize
a society that doesn't rely on these
regular blob bots
but of course now we are in a very
interesting situation where
um where christianity is kind of to a
certain extent we're on its course right
so now
we're in these apocalyptic times where
we got rid of paganism
paganism doesn't work anymore well there
are some mobs out there but nobody
really buys into it right i mean it's
like niches
here and there this is not causing a an
entire society to
to find to find this doesn't calm down
an entire society anymore right
so we don't know that yet but yeah okay
well it's become a kind of form of
entertainment
on some level i think coming we can have
the an object that is
hijacked by a dictator that's of course
always a possibility right but even that
will not last long that will end with
with a with a war that ends us all or it
will disappear again just like the nazis
disappeared it's just not not
it's just not workable it's not working
anymore that and the two that
that train left 2000 years ago you
cannot i don't think it's possible to
actually have
oh you had stalin for 30 years you had
mao in china for 30 years and you had
palpatine china
in cambodia for a couple of years there
aren't successful societies that people
look up to
with great economic growth and stuff
like that i mean they're kind of like a
bit like well
these are failed attempts to create
order right
yeah i i i would say though that the
only reason why the woke
culture today isn't more successful
because the woke people haven't realized
they're fighting a symbolic war
rather than a physical actual war but
when they realized that they could take
weapons into their hands and quickly
shift
that's why i think it's dangerous today
i think that i think people are getting
killed now in america and and
that that is because some of these guys
especially the antifa guys and certainly
some of the black lives matter guys
already
and the patriot prayer guys on the other
hand probably have realized that no no
wait a second we gain by picking up real
weapons and killing each other for real
which is probably what we wanted all
along
what the whole people haven't realized
is that when they go into symbolic
warfare they attack people like me for
example in scandinavia
i just returned the favor and my youtube
audiences go up
but once you realize that this was
actually your social biological program
doesn't say they should be symbolic it
should be physical and actual
then they will go after people hey where
were we yeah where were we
thomas is looking up something yeah
because i
actually feel a bit uh i was rambling
when uh
when you asked me about this paglia
stuff and uh so i looked it up now it's
this book called the renaissance mimetic
theory by wolfgang pallava
which is a very nice summary of of uh of
girardi
actually also talks about a lot of other
thinkers and he writes
so despite the proximity of paglian
girard with respect to the relationship
of sexuality and violence
however the difference between these two
thinkers is important for an
understanding of the mimetic theory
paglia completely avoids the memetic
cause of violence in the sexual realm
arguing instead of the connection of the
two phenomena is a natural constant
sexuality and violence she says are
intrinsically connected and therefore
necessarily problematic
so and i agree with gerard here
yeah not paglia so paglia i mean of
course these two do think
sexuality is less inherently problematic
than people
than people claim and this is this is an
eternal beef that i have with
with christians who are obsessed with
make turning
sexuality into an inherent problem and
not seeing that it's not
sexuality as as as sexuality that is the
problem but it's the
it's the envy and the jealousy that is
associated with
sexuality that is not skillful i think
that would be
the precise formulation okay great it's
kind of rare
isn't it to to find sexuality that isn't
you know
uh no i mean that's the thing is that i
mean people
need to be skilled in sexuality you need
to yeah
and it's it's it's getting more and more
problematic to do that in our society
because we're getting more and more
puritan
that means that people get more and more
unskilled in sexuality
and they will get in more and more
trouble so it's kind of like a vicious
it's a vicious circle right so so more
puritanism
less education and less less less skill
and more problems so and that leads to
more puritanism so
we're kind of in a very interesting uh
uh spiral
i agree on this one that means we
haven't we haven't gone pagan about
sexuality at all we've gone sort of
even more christian than christianity
about it because victorian
almost no no no the thing is that the 20
year olds today no no the 20 year old so
they're having tons of sex
but it's very [ __ ] up right
so what they're doing for example is
that uh they have new
numerality where it's like if you're 25
and have sex with somebody 17
it's like the worst thing ever but you
can have really hardcore cytomasochistic
sex to be 80 years old if your partner
is
19 or something like that it's just a
whole new
moralism that makes no sense at all
except that there must be some kind of
morality around it
and that to me is a christian heritage
because these kids have no idea what
sexuality is
they it can be fostered to it at all
it's basically through
pornography and that's it and
pornography is not a guide towards
sexuality
pornography is just like walking into
this land and think it's a university it
isn't it's disneyland right
but it's not a university you don't
learn anything through pornography at
all
you just you just mimic you just mimic
whatever it happens so i guess we're
agreed that the only real people
let me finish what you're way louder you
can take it again you're way louder than
we are now so is that okay
the volume is louder you are way louder
than we are i don't know
okay i'm sorry then your turn perfect
yeah
well i just want to say that that you
know i think we're all agreed that
the tantric sexuality is perhaps the
only you know proper route here but
that's all i wanted to say i mean what
in terms of healthy sexuality
what else is there uh i mean
what i mean i always think about as uh
of bdsm as western tantra well sure yeah
i mean there's no out there i mean it's
like an amazing
an amazing community with a lot not of
know-how and i agree i agree
we went to the european men's gathering
last week and we all know the first rule
in these gatherings is that fix your
damn sex life otherwise your brothers
can't trust you
it's not the normal rule and it can be
done and it's done by almost all of them
so
it must not be problematic so we're
looking at a trade-off here between east
and west
if we're looking at the overall
conversation tonight
we still haven't gotten to how east
tries to solve the problem between karma
and forgiveness which the west
or the middle east and the west did
better right uh the problem though with
the with the west is that it arrived
with the problem with sexuality here
with pogba versus gerard
clearly shows and sherrod is right about
that the problem wasn't sexuality itself
sexuality is ambivalent correct it's so
is subjectivity so is science so
so that that doesn't have to be a
problem at all the problem with
sexuality it's not
i put sexuality and violence into the
category of pathos and i think pathetic
narrative is completely underrated in
our society today
that's a sexuality violence pops up in
all the wrong places and that's getting
gay it's getting increasingly
problematic that's where pogba is on to
something and i completely agree with
that
obviously with the pathos needing to be
there next to the logos and the mythos
but in the east we need to go back to
the east since and this is my experience
from
both zoroastrianism buddhism and daoism
is that none of them have a major
problem with sexuality
yeah those three religions because
they've tantric traditions
has solved their problems when i became
a zoroaster and you know converted
early 1990s and i started hanging out
with zoroastrians from america and india
and europe alike
you know it was just like yeah you get
married because you actually unified two
different families so there's like two
clans get together and the way to tie
them together is a married
and that's like a company running
together which is actually why they have
a very low divorce rate
you know you should actually men and
women should meet and say let's run a
corporation together and call it a
family
that's a very good idea of a family so
they do that right and they have larger
more extended families that are actually
valid
and they hold so they have a very low
divorce rate brilliant
now the trick is then what do you do
with your sexuality and they just looked
at me just like well
who you sleep with is a totally
different story wherever you
execute your sexuality and you use that
energy obviously
very small part of it is going to be for
reproductive purposes which means your
husband or your wife is not that
interested
now there might be part seasons or
esther's out there disagreeing in public
about this but they would certainly
private agree because this is how they
live also i don't find a major problem
in sexuality in israel i think israelis
or jews in general are much more relaxed
about sexuality than christians and
muslims are yeah
so so that's not a major problem yet the
problem is when we approach
islam and christianity the pop religions
of the west
is that suddenly sexuality itself is
seen as the problem
i wonder if it's because there isn't a
strong matriarchal culture like there's
not women involved
somehow in uh in in dealing with
sexuality like i mean this was something
i got from paglia too
since we're speaking of her she
mentioned you know in the east you have
you have tantric women teachers yeah but
it's not like feminism has helped us
well no it's not feminism it's it's it's
it's tradition right it's like
there is a tradition of a different kind
of female right than than mother mary
and and
and ver you know than this soft kind of
kind of female there's well i would
agree because then if islam is the worst
case here then certainly if you lock up
women behind the jobs and things and
lock them up in a house and
you have to [ __ ] each other as men
before you're allowed to [ __ ] women and
when you do you might rape them
gets worse right so but you know
pagan wasn't nice either like so so uh
yeah it's nasty uh but again if you
create larger gatherings the social
becomes larger forms than clan or tribe
and clan tribe you can contain sexuality
per se
then if you have larger communities you
need prohibitions and these prohibitions
are ultimately not about
controlling sexuality because that's
just creating pressure cookers
so anybody would know is rather about
you know letting it out somewhere
and then use it for constructive
purposes and the way you do that is
you avoid making it a topic event
but return to the education the weakness
of the east in all of this is that maybe
that insult sexuality better than the
west did
but you still got the problem with karma
and this is an acute problem in india
where i work a lot these days because in
india
they are now mimicking the west on a
massive scale and they have all the
programmers and the coders of the world
and they have now a huge huge industry
employing tens of millions of people
who basically do all the program and the
coding you know computers for the rest
of the world
now that's a massive industry in india
it creates very little value though
because this this is low pay this is
like this is like
the factories of our age right so the
problem then is how can india become
more competitive by becoming more
entrepreneurial
and here is a problem you can in some
indian cults and some minority religions
like jainisms or asians and find a lot
of entrepreneurship
that is very specialized and gilded the
problem is
india's society doesn't in general have
an entrepreneurial spirit to it indians
go to america and then they become
bosses big companies they do not
necessarily innovate they're just
brilliant at mimicking
but the problem with indian culture is
that because it's tied to karma it's
incredibly hard for an indian to be
allowed to make mistakes
i would say this is still the pagan part
it's an unforgiving
uh uh notion of karma again
i think the brilliance with christianity
was properly practiced especially in
southern europe where
capitalism started was that this is the
root of capitalism this is
the brilliance of capitalism and
capitalism started with the bazaars
along the silk route
what was so great about the silk road
and the bazaars was it just the trade
no it was also the production and the
production went on all along the silk
road and
you know goods were transported back and
forth along the silicon
how did that happen it was
entrepreneurial so you
learned from your master but you could
also add innovation
so you could develop the products make
them better and better and improve on
them all the time
and to me this is the central
social value of forgiveness it's not
about mercy being nice to people
it's really about implementing an idea
that you can actually create same
engineering culture
an architectural culture you could you
could innovate and be entrepreneurial in
a culture
if you add tons of forgiveness to the
system
yeah that might be right i know i
remember like the the tibetans never
invented anything other than butter tea
right they had this very very complex
you know
deep spirituality but but they have they
don't have any entrepreneurial
aspect at all but still i suspect that
buddhism calmed down the lunch mobs in
the east so why wouldn't buddhism then
have some kind of entrepreneurial aspect
to it
where would entrepreneurism come from in
china
um is it buddhism confusion is a
modalism
um probably doubts i don't know probably
a mix of buddhism and taoism
it wouldn't be confusionism we should
invite a chinese person to discuss that
because obviously there's a lot of
entrepreneurial spirit going in china
which communism then prevents and stops
and tries to milk
but still it's happening undeniably
happening the chinese are
inventing they have an inventing culture
japan
japan has an innovative culture they
have shinto islam and buddhism as the
two main religions korea is an
innovative culture it is buddhism again
so yeah it's influenced by
zoroastrianism i've argued that zen
and zion and china are essentially
trade route religion so that means
there's don't waste them in buddhism
you're iconoclastic as well right you
know you can kill the buddha
like uh uh you know there's this
expression if you meet the buddha kill
the buddha and there's
there's a sort of uh you can break
something and then and then do it again
probably maybe that's part of it
there is a lot i think there's you know
there is there is a a a big
aspect of repentance uh in that culture
and you you do things
wait i make a difference between
forgiveness and repentance yeah what's
the difference
repentance is that you stand before a
perfect god and you've proven to be
imperfect
so you've done something that's been
imperfect so you ask for repentance
meaning you're forgiven for that
specific acts you can go back into the
perfect realm
there's no learning involved if you do
repent
that's so that's not that's islam that's
the problem with islam islam is strictly
repentance culture means that you did
bad
and if you don't excuse yourself for
doing bad you'll get killed now but then
you might get a second chance but
there's really no learning going on
because you stand before perfection
if you stand for perfection that's just
repentance
that is the difference between
repentance and forgiveness that i find
incredibly important here
because you cannot create a thriving
entrepreneurial culture
on religion that only allows for
repentance but if religion allows for
forgiveness and puts forgiveness at the
center you eliminate two problems
one you go innovative and two you avoid
the lynch mob
because on this what do you think thomas
would you have any
i think one here very good yeah so so
basically um
so so turn the other cheek is a
mechanism to avoid escalation
so that's one thing and then but the
other thing is as what alexander points
out is also that that you need to
you need to be able to you can fail and
then learn from your mistakes and try
again
so these are kind of two aspects of of
forgiveness so you avoid escalation and
and you you enter a learning process so
yeah
yeah that that makes a lot of sense yeah
and the scapegoat cannot be scapegoated
without problems at least if the
scapegoat can be forgiven because the
scapegoat
has done certain things that means you
got to go pagan
to kill the scapegoat you can't stay
within the christian realm so even if
you got a christian lynch mob say going
after the jew
you're absolutely correct to say that
stop being christians when they start
doing the programs that kill the jews
because that's not christian at all
i see i see paganism in christianity
everywhere now after reading girard it's
so
it's also such a relief right because
now i can say like well
the aspects of christianity that are
always disliked these are pagan aspects
and the aspects of christianity also
like well this makes a lot of sense
these are actually in my as far as i can
understand now
these are actually the very old aspects
of christianity that turn christianity
into
into a success like for example the so
the problematic deeply problematic
aspects like the witch burnings and
and you know the pogroms against the
jews and stuff like that that's all
just chris christians get going turtle
pagan
it's uh it's quite fascinating i mean
you see a lot of a lot of opinions now a
lot of
people who consider themselves very very
christian they're not christian at all
they're pagans for example also
christians who very
who judge other religions this is not a
christian thing to do
well they got a problem we discussed
before and that's the elimination of the
bard absolute so the bard absolute is
there and it's
it's it's uh it's foundational for
zoroastrianism and judaism doubtlessly
so i mean it's just
there's something behind the bar
absolutely you must not go behind
because if the bard absolute is removed
it's nothing prevents you from looking
straight into the eyes of god right
and protestantism played this fully
luther played his fault
this is like lutheran cow it's like the
direct relationship to god
makes christianity unique nobody else
nobody else allows to talk directly to
god
actually that is alien that is alien to
people the bard absolute there has to be
something between
humans and god and the priesthood has to
make sure that door is locked
and that is key to zoroastrianism
judaism and it's precisely how you avoid
a mass religion to go pagan is i think
paganism could sneak into christianity
certainly into islam the back door
because these religions
had no barred absolute and if you don't
have a bad absolute paganism come back
can come back in because if
if you have a direct access to god then
god is also reflected in your direct
actions that means your pagan instincts
because it can be completely divine
because you know the will of god
people who do not follow the will of god
they sh they can be scapegoated is that
is that your
yes yes exactly that makes a lot of
sense so the root of fundamentalism
which is unique to christianity and
islam it doesn't make any sense to have
fundamentalism and buddhism is harassing
judaism because these are complex
religious that basically says you don't
know [ __ ] anyway right
go it's a long path to learn by the way
there's a part absolute at the end you
need to pass through it's called
enlightenment
in buddhism and it's really really hard
to get there right and at least it's
tantrum sutra and buddhist teachings too
so rasterism has the same thing it has a
definite bardocks which you must not go
beyond
the priests even have their own religion
which is separate from yours
you're taught a religion that works for
you it's about your asha so this
religion you're being taught it will
work
that's so rationalism it's called
masterism and the separate from
mosleyism is
organism so they're separated in in
judaism this is clearly the case here
what the jews find so disgraceful
about christ dying on the cross not that
he died on the cross and they might even
have made a mistake he might have been a
good man
and maybe he could even teach them a
lesson about scapegoating they like that
but what the jews found problematic
about christ on the cross that was
described in the bible
is that the curtain fell down in the
temple and there was
direct access to the innermost sacred
room for anybody and everybody to see
this is this is today when we see
today's society with transparency
and the demand for everything to be seen
and people opening up their their homes
and everything
what i call porn afflation with john in
our books we call it the porn inflated
society
this con it's constant need that
everything opened up for everybody to
see
that comes from a terrible mistake
christianity in islam
and this is the idea that everything
should be opened up for everybody
because we have the divine right to see
absolutely everything and see straight
into the ass of god if you want to
and this opens the door so that when
paganism then comes back with the
vengeance it comes back
aggressively these cultures this has
cursed islam and christianity
all along and that is the price they
paid for being pop religions
they made religion easy they packaged
themselves to sell it to the masses
i i i just say i disagree i think that
you are being way too harsh on both
christianity and islam i think that
you know islam has been around for a
long time you know if you've
if you've seen a building like the
alhambra right i mean you can see like
what what
incredible beautiful things islam can
can can accomplish
so i think that all religions will have
a
non-functional pop part that is like
completely
you know kind of a perversion and then
they will have a core that is kind of
like well you know this is the stuff
that actually makes it work
and i think it's very interesting to
look at religions like like that so
so i i will gladly take you to the
guardians of yas did iran you see the
world hamburgers mimicked from it wasn't
from a muslim heritage at all
so no i i disagree that islam really has
contributed as much as being claimed i
mean because
has been the world religion for 1400
years actually i'm kind of like more
proposing a research project because
you know gerard has has has done very
little with respect to other religions
i mean he he wrote one book about uh
about brahmanism i believe
but uh i haven't read it yet it's on my
to-do list but he hasn't really
he he limited himself very much to
christianity i think that the gerardian
project should look at other religions
like buddhism
sutra and tantric buddhism and islam and
basically see like how how do they
these religions work and why did they
stick around so long
because most religions they just they
just come up and they disappear right
yeah why are these religions successful
so what made them
and most functional and what makes them
dysfunctional i think these are very
interesting questions
most of buddhism is is probably pop
religion too i mean people in in
people believe in the pure land and
they're going to go to the pure land
it's very very pop religion
most of it i would say probably but
that's the fact that i think there's a
function of that i think there's a
function there needs to be
but that's a false religion version of
it don't mistake that for the proper
religion in this case
well i mean there's a billion buddhists
and most of them are sort of
sort of i mean there's always there's
people who always
turn it into something that that works
and which which works at a very
superficial level right
i mean it's always going to happen that
happens with buddhism hinduism
christianity yeah but don't flatten it
out here
we must be able to criticize certain
religions for certain basic talents they
believe in they are different
after all and i think islam was popular
because it was simplistic
and that has been its curse ever since
and the really simplistic religions if
we want to simplistic religious
we have a we have a reversed order of
the silk road tribe that we of course
admire we love zarastis and buddhism and
dallas and that's the situation i really
you know
grounded now but um the other version of
that is the disney world triad
the district will try to jehovah's
witnesses and hormones and
scientologists
so as you can see religion has gone on a
downward slope the last five thousand
years
yet up with the most vulgar silliest
versions of it in america in the last
100 years
so you know the the disabled tribe is
interesting for a comparative study with
buddhism and daoism or westernism
what really happens when you go pop
culture in terms of religion i mean
scientology is just hysterical in that
sense it's just
it's just you you pay your way to go to
different planets
it's just it's just yeah but it's
fascinating
actually that religion can go that far
and get that silly
and you can't compare those religions
with the traditions we're talking about
what about the catholic church for
example that is that
is that a pop religion or i mean most of
it or
there's a folk religion element that's
why you added the saints
and that was smart that's why
catholicism will survive protestantism
prosthetism is dying catholicism will
still be around for a long time to come
and and simply because it allows for a
folk religion which you can talk to the
saints and the saints will then talk to
god
they've reinstated the bardab suit in a
very clever way
and you know that's that's an
interesting that's an interesting
thought but then they're actually
actually reinstated i mean this is
basically what i pointed out right so
that you will have like
you will have like let's say pop
religion and then you have something
like let's say something that is a bit
less uh
a bit more refined so and and i guess
it's the same
it's like that with all religions right
so then you would kind of would kind of
expect
a certain certain religion has a court
that that is kind of
to some extent integrated and valuable
and then and then a lot of
of uh of stuff on top of that that you
could call pop religion
yeah you had the same thing in islam you
have you have sufism that
came along along the silk route and was
devised essentially it's harassed in the
buddhist teachings developed under an
islamic umbrella and of course it's the
most interesting part
artistically theologically anything you
like within islam is sufism and there's
very little islamic to be honest about
it it's it's just it just yeah so
catholicism you know realized we need a
bard absolute okay so
have martyrs so then become saints
they're not scapegoats because
scapegoating ended with christ no
they're models role models so you can
actually talk to them
and because they live this fulfilling
and rich lives the church
in communication with god is decided we
can turn these into role models or
forefathers
or four mothers that you can actually
pray to so you don't have just virgin
mary harry all of a sudden have all
these scents you can pray to
that's a much richer religion than
protestantism that then comes much later
and says that oh we're going to print
the bible because to print the bible
your local language will have direct
access to god
so he can remove all the saints and
clean out all the churches to make the
minimalists
has looked at that so there's there's
scholar barth
um which probably you know considered
one of the greatest theologians of the
20th century and
one of the things that he pointed out is
that well there's no god behind jesus
so he was aware of this problem i think
and he solved it by saying well you know
often christians think of you know you
have jesus and then god is behind that
right from something in the sky that
looks down
and he points out well jesus is the only
thing you have there's no god behind
jesus
you can't decouple it and that is that
is a very interesting thought
yeah it's the saurus and mastan ahura
but
they're both primordial in
zoroastrianism they're not personified
that's kind of like why zizek would say
that uh you know be a christian atheist
and
of some kind if there's no guide behind
jesus then there's
just man right it seems that i ended up
somewhere uh
somewhere along that part yes yeah it's
the kind of escape what the theologians
did in the 20th century but anyway
uh back to orthodoxy and orthodoxy gets
into the same problem the way to try to
solve is by going modest so
neoplatonism is dominated in orthodox
theology
and that's if you convert to orthodox
christian it's probably because of a
modest worldview you don't buy into the
platelet dualism
it's it's it's the new plate and it's a
shaped orthodoxy and that was a major
shift for them
that's how they tried to solve the bard
absolute because the bard absolutes is
automatically reinstated if you go for a
modest world view
it's the price you pay for monism
okay unpack that a bit okay so
if you go for dualism your soul can be
free from your body
your soul can then be perceived as being
divine and that allows for the bard
absolute to be removed
that's what all gnostics are trying all
the time they realize they cannot become
divine in the human body
so they hate the body consider their own
spirit to be superior
to the body and suddenly it's even
superior to anything else inside this
divine
so gnostics tend to be very
self-preoccupied narcissists usually
pillar saints who think of themselves
being superior to others and
usually very envious of other people's
sex lives okay that's the probably
gnostics
so rasters knew it and they just wanted
to get rid of them they just they
weren't even heretics they were just
like
trash it's just like get them out of the
way like marx would consider the lump
and proletariat just they're out of the
way they're destroying our revolution
get them out of the way
so there were the gnostics and
gnosticism stayed because of dualism and
the radical dude is of course separation
of body mind means that
all of the world is the dual means it's
not unified
it's not connected it's evil and good or
whatever that can't be unified at all
your body your mind cannot be unified
and you have to pick one of them and
then if you go for the mind you got to
get rid of the body and then you start
hating sexuality and in through the door
you got the problem sexuality
christianity created because of except
for dualism
now in modernism you don't accept that
everything is tied to everything else
but you can allow as many attributes as
you like so for example god can have
different faces and still be one god
yeah
elohim in judaism elohim is a pluralist
you don't say allah you say yeah you say
gods
for god meaning you got yava and you got
el
and you got adonai and they're separated
and the same thing is rasterism you
separate mastanura they're not separate
gods
they're just different names for god
they're usually used separately
because being and master is mind
and because mind is within being and
being as
is within mind in zoroastrianism they're
in parallel with one another
and they together are the divine
so you look up to the divine and try to
model yourself accordingly
so you might have role models in between
say mobeds or ushas or military leaders
whenever you look up to your mentor or
your father or your mother whatever
you look up to other role models in your
life and you try to mimic them to be as
they are and grow up
and you have a divine ideal that then
grown-ups look up to and then grown-ups
become models for children
so you got a chain here of things you
should mimic that's how they solve the
mimiky the problematic desire
so the that's the rasterism version of
that and you can do that within a modest
universe
but then the bird absolute comes in
because for the child
the grown-ups are about absolute you are
literally three years old
you're three you're not 30. when you're
30 years old you're literally not
90. you cannot be an elder when you're
30 years old you're probably in the
middle of your reproductive phase you
work hard you have kids right
you can then become an elder what do the
elders do the elders look up to assumed
and look up to the priesthood
and the priesthood then look up to the
divine so there's always somebody you
look up to who you're not
yet at and you take this is a rasterism
all the way to your death
and when when you die you strive for a
mere thought which is transcendence
but you reach harvard which is fullness
so you reach fullness and you die you
can go to peace and you can die
because a meditation will then be your
heritage
so whatever you created during your life
will then be inherited
and used by others to create an even
better world which is zoroastrianism's
unique points
and this this idea of fraction of the
ever-improving world
is central to zerastreamism you can only
do that with the bard absolutely you
have several board absolutes on the way
but if you remove them like islamic
christianity did
there's not even a difference between a
child and a god
there's no coincidence that you have
child gods and god children in these
religions
they do not exist in judaism they did
not exist in buddhism they did not
existed zoroastrianism the idea that god
can be a child and the child can be god
it's actually what i would say is islam
and christianity's problem
so you get allah who is a boy who's a
god and in christianity you get
the boy who's born with wisdom so this
is the
critical question in christianity you
you get the boy in the cradle
he's apparently god so he must be
perfect and he must have ultimate wisdom
he's never lived in life how can you
have ultimate wisdom he hasn't lived
alive
and that's of course why he goes all the
way to the cross you don't ever hear
about his sex life
because if he had a sex life he would be
perfect
so he starts with a mother next team in
the cradle and he ends up on the cross
next to his mother
and it's essentially a boy pharaoh all
the way
no i i don't really agree that with that
i mean the whole point of of uh
of of crisis just to to expose the the
victimization mechanism that's it
that's it i mean in that sense christ
isn't really i mean is an example in the
sense that um
that he avoids the memetic escalation
and things like that but
i mean you can't just take christ as a
as a uh as a role model it's
no no no no i'm not saying i'm saying
that the problem is a religion the boy
and god are the same thing if you remove
the bar dab so that's what you get
because the barred absolutes that we go
through in life are the things we cannot
yet be
but that we strive towards that is the
point with taunton too sutra is there to
strive towards tantra
you can stay in sutra and be a
reasonable citizen in a society
and you can just find out the tantra is
too hard for you to stomach
then don't go there you're allowed to
stay within the sutra and be
perfectly okay actually if you go into
the tantic mode and you weren't prepared
for it
and you went in there anyway you [ __ ] up
yourself miserably and become a drug
abuse and all kinds of things
yeah that's exactly the point with the
bard absolute that's why buddhism has it
your religion has it my religion has it
judaism has it
the problem was that islamic
christianity removed it to turn
themselves into pop religions
and the really absurd versions of that
the disallowing disa world tribe in
america
have no idea what a bard absolute even
is
that is problematic the prohibition that
religion teaches
to contain human desire starts with the
barred absolute
without it you run into problems all
along well in zen
and zen there's gradual enlightenment
and sudden enlightenment
gradual enlightenment is step step by
step by step
right where there's also this this kind
of
absolute too uh um there's this there's
this
sudden there's a sudden enlightenment so
so
it's almost like both are contained both
views are contained so you would say
that you could be like a savior person
if you're young
in buddhism also i'll give you another
example
um in in in judaism you have the
the secret torah and you have the oral
torah the oral torah is what moses gave
the jews with all these rules
they have to follow and that was a
punishment because they weren't ready
for the secret
for the they weren't ready to get the
holy spirit directly
they weren't ready for that so actually
the torah that the oral torah is a
punishment to prepare
prayer was a punishment from god
apparently
whereas whereas the real thing is the
sikh is the is the um
is it is the um the secret torah not the
secretary
the other just the oral torah the direct
realization
right i see this i see this
like past the bard absolute there are
there are there are there are no stages
and rules and
and there's no suture anymore um
and that's when you meet that but you're
right yeah you have to be prepared for
that so
so so uh no there's no sutra in your
life but you need to teach sutra to
others
that's we become a real leader sure
right that's why the jewish religion is
there
i find this fascinating because the
natural reaction today especially among
young smart men and we have quite a few
of them around us in the election deep
web in other places
is that they all go for alchemy and they
want to invent sort of a
an intelligent credible real version of
chaos magic and things like that right
now
they're really going towards freemasonry
and orders again
uh that that is the bard absolute in
sort of civil life that's the civil west
it's just like
you would go into those orders because
if religion was too childish and forgave
you for anything you did you could at
least go into these orders which then
became part of religion
and i think they were again invented to
sort of back up the lack for bard
absolutes within christianity
and that's why freemasonry for example
which is the beauty of the united states
of america is the constitution was
created by freemasons they did
fantastic things and they were very
inspired by persians through the french
and i love these traditions because
because i i think it's very healthy but
the the reaction from guys that go
anti-walk after they're tired of being
anti and they want to be active rather
than reactive
is that patrick ryan does this daniel
faraga does this owen cox does it
all these guys they're really sincerely
interested in alcohol and chaos magic
but not from the point of like
i'm a teenager trying to find my
identity this is cool thing to do you're
going to satanist death cults or
whatever i'll listen to every metal no
no
they are serious about this they're
serious about rewriting the history of
the alchemists
and um i find that interesting it is the
rediscovery of the bard episode how
incredibly important it is for culture
and maybe we're finally then waking up
to what i'm really
going towards here which is what i call
the adultification of religion and the
adultification of the west
yeah the principal exploitation has to
be replaced by the principle implotation
we have to preach equitopianists and we
have to preach cosmopolitanism we also
have to preach the tower of god which
that
there are certain things you cannot
achieve in your life you will have to
die before those things can be achieved
maybe your children will okay that is
the bard episode in its absolute form
and we call it the tower of god in our
work next to the garden of god and the
city of god
but i think that these ideas are coming
back they're all built on the idea that
if you don't reinstate the bard
absolutely dramatically and this is
of course teaching tantra
philosophically to the west
there is no way the west could achieve
any of this i mean
the direct access society the the
shortcut society
the quick fix society all these
pathologies we see today that
i'm gonna have it and i'm gonna have it
now
that the commercialism you know brought
in that if i want this i can have it no
you can't
actually you probably never can have it
even if you try it you won't have it
yeah and why is that what if you did
meet god directly like
isn't that the ultimate religious
prohibition that's needed today is to
stop this porn inflation and the mass
narcissism and the world culture and all
that
is to go back and say no you will not
have any of these things or at least
very few of them and only if they fit
your archetypes you can serve the
community by having them and it's going
to take you
years and years to get it
this is the bird absolute i think it's
absolutely key it's the end chapter of
our book
we tied to the dark renaissance and the
return of the bard absolute
but we're going to end the book on that
note and we're not going to end the book
with forgiveness we're not going to
end up with some sort of syrupy ending
saying yeah i know some of those gotta
come along and save us early third time
at all i think that's
exactly the wrong message today
absolutely this is here so don't worry
about it
no not at all the sausage can be a
machine
but if the sausage is the machine in a
collaboration with some humans and
certainly in all of them then that
collaboration does not give the right
for all humanity to pass through to the
next stage i don't think the exit is
is at all for the masses i think the
exodus is for a small elite and a few
machines
to be honest and i think that's the
brutal truth we need to teach
you know you you've got to call the new
book the exodus i i
i honor you for that purpo for that
suggestion but it's going to be called
process and event because of the book
but the overall trilogy will be called
the exonology i'm going to talk to you
on about it but
i think since there's some digital
libido and prostate event together
all three of them are the externality
does that make sense
yeah that's that's a good overall title
for sure yeah
that makes sense to me but forgiveness
has to be in here i'm
getting this raster version of it i
think i can get the jewish version
i'm interested in the christian version
of it not because subscribe to it i
think it's a bit of a cheap shot i think
bitch's critique
was irrelevant but it has worked it's
worked wonderfully
it is it is why christianity is being
imported in korea and china at the
moment it's only because
it's associated with prosperity and
success
so if buddhism didn't provide enough
innovation energy
to the chinese and the koreans and the
taiwanese they're certainly now on a
massive scale importing christianity
the vulgar protestant american version
of it so what
it's all about try and try again
and americans do try and they fail and
they try again
interesting at least before they became
woke
yeah so it's essential to the heroic
that i've been talking about for years
i've never
i've never talked about the heroic being
tied to forgiveness but i absolutely now
see the connection
and i'm still interested in buddhism
must have worked a lot with this
compared to hinduism and
asian paganism so i'm interested how
buddhism solved that problem how you get
out of the karma circle
not too cheaply that was nietzsche's
point his criticism of
christianity was not you couldn't get
out of the circle it was rather that you
got out too deeply
again the whole point is to get out and
get out of the circle and in buddhism
that's that's the entire
that's the entire point is to get out of
the the wheel
but that's your next life and the next
life of the next life or can we give
reincarnation here and say that buddhism
doesn't really preach reincarnation oh
it doesn't you don't need to you don't
need
the reincarnation is irrelevant to that
you're you're trying to wake up
you know out of the karmas but you're
going to save yourself in that sense you
must forgive yourself
how does it work it's just i'm just
fascinated with because obviously it has
at least partly solved this problem
because there's less
less lynch mobbing in the culture which
to me is evidence that
somehow there's a forgiveness mechanism
working because i think the forgiveness
mechanism is what
ultimately de-instrumentalizes the lynch
mod
it's it's just they hate when you say
there's forgiveness because if you
allow forgiveness they can't kill the
bait yeah
well if you it can't at least they can't
kill the bait without being guilty for
it
and they don't want the guilt they don't
want the guilt they don't want the shame
they're terrified of that the lyrical
wants
to be an objective collectively go after
the scapegoat
and that's why they all throw rocks at
the same time so none of them is guilty
of killing the scapegoat
oh it just died right and it died and
there was release from tension
but what gets hard to do is not only the
savior standing there
saying that you must not kill the
scapegoat because you will repeat that
all over and over again next time is
your turn
no this is not an ethical scapegoating
christian
the christian savior is not only a
defender of the scapegoat in that sense
the christian savior says those of you
who have no sin
you throw the first rock that is that is
the end
that is de-recognizing
or and sees that it's his own face or
something like that
maher is the devil or whatever
one of you guys is an echo onto your
microphone right now you don't want that
maybe me okay yeah go ahead please
explain to me i love this
six realms yeah
i really like this uh this uh this
teaching so so yeah
so the buddhism so buddhism kind of so
you you can you can think of these six
realms of the realms in which you can be
born right reincarnated but chogyam
trump
actually used them very much as ways of
being
right so so many people who do
meditation and do these
follow these these uh you know new age
teachings that they try to get to the
god realm
so that's the realm of perfect being
right that's
where you're enlightened you're you're
perfectly happy and you're going to be
there
so but that's that's that's not the goal
of it that's just one of these six
realms and the other other realms are
the hungry the
the jealous god real where you you this
is kind of like
uh you're very rich but you you won't
still want to be richer that's the
that's the
that's the jealous god ryan then you
have the hungry ghost realm which is the
addictions you have the animal realm
which is stupidity and
slavery and so so in each of these
realms so these are these are the hell
realms the one you're missing here
the hell realm is the is the realm of
violence and war and
hatred yeah and in each of these realms
so these are beings right you have god
beings you have hell beings you have
hungry ghost beings
but you know in every realm there is a
buddha and that means that
that your misery or your problem or
you're being stuck in the god realm or
in the anger of of the hell realm that's
an opportunity for a buddha
to step in and help you but you can
always emerge
in that realm as a buddha in your anger
or in your in your
stupidity you can actually act as a
buddha
and that's a very i think that's a very
very nice teaching and basically
it's not so much about um about avoiding
these realms
which would be kind of the the sutrick
approach or and the approach of
christianity
but it's about recognizing in which real
realm you are and by
recognizing it you can you can transcend
it
yeah so if you're in the hell around
it's anger realm you you transcend that
to clarity and if you're in the
ignorance realm
you you transcend that to sort of being
very open
uh if you're in the hungry ghost realm
uh you would trans i don't know what
that what how motivational speed
motivation and speed uh you're very
motivated to do stuff and in the god
realm everything is
is so prosperous for you so you're in a
very good uh position to help other
people who are not so
prosperous so in that sense it's not so
much about because
you so the the buddhism is not so much
about
about escaping the cycle it's actually
accepting the
cycle completely as your as your way of
being
there is no but it's alchemical too it's
it's it's transforming that it's
you brought up alchemy uh alexander i
think that vagina path is profoundly
alchemical it's about transforming
those uh those realms i love it i guess
this is this is great this explains a
lot because
although i'm familiar with it the way
you explain it now in this context means
you create a sort of
very concrete micro ethics just like
these are the different answers though
they also rhyme very well with all three
narratives pathos logos and mythos
because you have the aspects of path as
long as it is so so the stories you tell
about yourself that's all about the
world are you pathetic or mythical
logical or the mixes of them
so the same thing matches these six six
realms too
but you actually then go into sort of
microethicals
you do concretely deal with these things
and that transformation you're talking
about here
is the shift i'm interested in because
the transformation is the goal
of why you have forgiveness is your
astronaut the forgiveness of strategism
is not there as a generous
thing to be thrown off because you have
you know your children of god and god is
merciful this is not about god looking
good
it's not about virtual signaling at all
no it's just about
no oh you made a mistake listen you've
got plenty of time to be child before
you become a grown
so why don't you try again okay you try
and try again and then you finally
transform and you become a grown up
in zoroastrianism so you stop being a
child you become a grown up and you take
on the responsibilities you go through
right of passage
it's a similar journey you make
different steps and again
there is a before and after this is
before you
walk into the realm and you're
confronted with all these things you
cannot avoid them and you must be there
and stay there with it
until you with the buddha's help or your
buddha as a role model
can be transformed yeah
again it it's i don't know if
prohibition is the right word the
religion deals with here it's more like
fostering us it's just like
yeah this is the right channel that now
get get in here in this channel and in
schooling it's education
it's like if you do this properly here
and it's been done before by many
instead of guessing what you're going to
do then you probably arrive in the right
place
now compare that for example to the idea
of contemporary secular sexuality
which is just that oh by the way uh
teenagers will find out for themselves
what it's like to [ __ ]
and they'll discover it naturally if we
just close down the warehouses and close
down pornography let's figure it out
so let's not have to educate them or
teach them about any of these things
mind-bogglingly
idiotic it is mind-boggling idiotic
exactly which means they will only go to
pornography and they have nowhere else
to go i thank god of these for that
because if they didn't even know that
what would they do to rape each other
what of course they get [ __ ] up
of course they have no idea what
sexuality is of course they can create
all kinds of weird moralities around it
because they live in a sort of
post-christian world where christianity
is still around but not supposed to be
there
the pagan alternatives is basically just
rape and take whatever you want and
leave
so you know it's it's well because they
don't understand the out
chemical aspect of sexuality right it's
again
children cannot invent a world of rules
and regulations then we get
lord of the flies we left sexuality in
contemporary society to
the kids and we left it to become lord
of the flies
it it's just it's just idiotic
it's idiotic it's just horrendous it's
just and then we put on bikinis on
two-year-olds as if the two-year-olds
must be protected from pedophiles it
just
completely deranged it's just
really really weird and it's gonna get
worse i think i think woke will can
fight down over the next few years at
least or woke fights down itself
as long as he stayed symbolic we're
happy with that and doesn't go
actually violent okay but you know if
if the [ __ ] ups that come next after
that are gonna stay with us for
much much longer and it's again the idea
that the
infant can learn
on their own from other infants how the
world operates six year olds watching
six year olds watching six year olds on
youtube
it's not a healthy environment at all
it's gonna go
it's gotta go really deranged before we
start realizing that's not how human
beings operate
they operate over across generations
they learn from the older generations
that's how you learn things
i think i think the search for mentors
is a healthy thing we see among the
young guys right now on the men's
movement
we embrace it because there's a lack of
mentors they go into alchemy and lodges
and
orders and things because that's when
you meet the other guys your own age
that is essentially what a really good
men's group is
like if you don't find elders find five
other guys your own age because together
you're 100 years old you have
five times 20 years life experience
that's not a bad start at all for a
men's group
i think these reactions that are coming
from the young smart kids right now are
very healthy and good
that means they're going necrocratic
they're gonna do fine they're going to
do well they're going to be engineers
programmers coders
they're going to create a technological
patrick and she's going to run the world
and men are going to take over again
process right some kind of process to go
through rather than just
this being through process and event
thrown into the world with
with nothing and just process is
childhood but the move from childhood to
adulthood is the event okay adulthood is
a process
you move from adulthood into elderhood
an event
oh that's another priesthood an event at
the priesthood for the divine
okay so these steps the part absolutes
we're supposed to go through say you go
you within sutra you're in process yeah
you go from sutra to tantra that's an
event
then you can move into tantra as a
process this is why we write a book
called prasan event is to discuss
and understand how you can be in a loop
where you can make mistakes
you can make them all over again and you
you learn from your mistakes and you get
ready and eventually whoop one day the
event happens and you can pass on to the
next
well that's it's not that you've
perfected sutra in some kind of a way
right you
to get to the event that you would go
into tantra like you don't become
perfect
oh you you become whole you you well you
don't even
become whole if there's there's an event
it's it's a it's a kind of uh
there's no perfection there's no no no
there's no perfection there's just
there's just it's not perfect completion
and perfection are different words
completion means you completed that
journey it doesn't mean you're perfect
at all
it's just that what you were supposed to
do there you've done it you're through
with that
you can move on to the next stage so
completion is not perfection remember
that in smarasian religion there is
completion there is no perfection
but we are in a we are in a very good
position and we are in a very good
position
because we have uh we have we have the
we have a deep theoretical framework to
understand tantra and
to understand sutra because we have
girard for sutra with very precise
description of desire
and then we have we have uh nietzsche
who has the tantric side
and they're they need to be united you
know like girard didn't quite uh
do nietzsche justice and of course
nietzsche was way too
i mean he just jumped into tantra and
rejected sutra completely
so in a sense we have like two
incomplete geniuses
and they need to be united so i guess
that's what you're going to do in your
book
on a better yeah and we got hagel and
white on the other side for the
metaphysics
yeah yeah yeah well those four are the
giant those four are the giants i agree
completely i'm willing to skip the less
he doesn't he doesn't
he doesn't he doesn't fulfill the
requirements there's something lacking
in him he was a
brilliant when he was younger but he
doesn't he doesn't he
the last just basically took made a
vulgar version of whitehead for the
europeans or something but he doesn't
qualify
i haven't i haven't studied the lesser
yet so but uh i have his
book on nature and the heidegger book on
nature so that's uh
that's the last book on each is
fantastic but it's a book on nietzsche
that's why it's great so you're starting
nietzsche through heidi and the laws and
started them in parallel
the book books came out the same year i
think or year in between
written independently of each other and
the long young the losses versus
and the old highly professionalistic
should be read comparatively next to
each other i completely understood
nietzsche after finishing that and then
i went back to red nature properly and
saw the patterns clearly
that's a great way of doing it and i
think the losses work in the 1960s
difference of repetition the logic of
sense completes whatever nietzsche
hadn't written or hide again britain
before
see that's completely nichianism and
that's where foucault
and les are nietzscheans in a way but
what then the loss went into after he's
[ __ ] a lot of students in paris in the
1960s and then he
got re made to this immensely over half
box called thousand plateaus and
you know uh antiochus and all that there
are marginal works
in the history of philosophy they really
are marginal works and they are the
works of course that scholarship
successfully attacks
and agent johnston successfully attacks
the american version of the losses
william connolly and jane bennett and
they're very sort of mediocre flat
philosophers
they're not very interesting they're
just too politically correct and all
that nonsense today it's just it's just
it's just not worth it where it's at
they're not phallic at all
it's way more interesting to start a
lamborghini to read william connolly or
or
jane bennett to get at a different
viewpoint and somebody
goes for the event fully embrace it
fully and works with the multitude and
with plurality and
and with the world that might not even
be held together what would it be like
you know marcus gabriel these guys they
all start from video
he's a great philosophy that he forces
you to rethink
and we do the event based on video we
say process and event
we seriously believe there's a phallic
event that happens in history that
changes the course of history
it's called technology if nothing else
but we also look at our own lives that
way
but it's then it's a normal logical
series of events but really
eventological events are the ones that
change this history forever
for all of humanity that can be a
narrative that can
that that can be sending rockets into
space and look down on the planet earth
and finally see what the planet earth
looks like from outer space
that alone like heidegger wrote 1958
blew our minds
right you know the atomic bomb 1945
sixth of august the world is forever
changed after that experience
there's no way back the atomic bomb
cannot be put back as a gene into the
bottle the genie is out we need to deal
with it we live in a world
post-atomic bomb it's an event so these
events
change history forever and this is by do
central thesis
this is anything but the eternal return
of the same
we left the eternal return of the same
we settled down and started storing
information
and we didn't repeat the same things
over and over again
we started making the world different
for good or bad
and that forever changes everything i
think this is zoroaster's idea
i i would say in terms of great ideas i
mean nietzsche and gerard are geniuses
and understanding the social
they're social philosophers but in terms
of just
new ideas out there that the nietzsche
and gerard work on other people's ideas
the new ideas are numerology was the
original idea we don't know who started
that
at least 200 000 years old probably more
than that it's just
it just came out of life itself and you
know social animals would be normal
logical or something
but then our numerology came came the
eventological idea that so roster three
thousand seven years ago
and the only other idea on a part with
that
is hegel's i did you start with negation
when you do dialectics
it's the only idea i can really think of
that is on a par with those two ideas
numerology eventology and dialectics
those hegelian dialectics in the sense
that
it starts with the negation subjectivity
starts with the void
that's a fantastic understanding of
subjectivity is
and then it keeps itself busy with
finding itself which is exactly how it
works right you know this hegel thing i
just
i need more time with it you know
you love it once you get there you love
it i mean you you think so much like a
hegelian already
and there is so much of hegel and
nietzsche there's no niche without hegel
and there's certainly tons of hegel in
gerard do and heidegger definitely deals
with stones to higgle too you
but in different ways you if you go back
to the origin you find even more than
these guys do
by the way salvation has released two
new books one of them is
absolute crap and it's called a left
that dare speak its name i
i became even less of a leftist after
afterlife
it's so horrible it's just slavo at his
worst he's just
he's just puking getting cute he's just
a
maniac on a drive where he's just
producing books
does he eat he probably eats hot dogs
until it kills him or something
he's terribly unhealthy you can tell he
doesn't even take a walk right he just
writes translators
like a maniac right but that book is
terrible
but the other new book which is hegel in
a wired brain
is fantastic and he
finally makes the right move against the
lures by saying that
somebody said this would be the lesson
century i think actually for
co-prophesied to said that in the 1980s
that
the future is the lesson h and then his
challenge just i said no
i'm i'm adamant it's going to be the
hegelian h and finally they get an age
is going to happen
and and he then takes hegel into
neuroscience and everything and you know
the first three pages of that book
contained more knowledge and more
original insight than the entire
uber of shisha last 10 years so the guy
has both written a crappy book i don't
know who put that together the
publishing company
and then obviously it's worked properly
on the other one which is where he's got
his heart
and and i think adrian johnstone
slavishing because they're now fighting
over hegel which is the right
interpretation of echo we're actually
very close to each other but
they've got a transcendental materialism
which is johnston they've got a
dialectical materialism which is
which is uh and we're going to kill
materialism all together with brady
island's help
and create a transcendental emergencism
instead
which i think is more hegelian there's
more spinosa and hegel than these guys
admit
what was that about spinoza oh
hegel is the coalition of kant versus
spinoza
so the spanish universe ends up flat
and no freedom no motivation no pathos
in it
it's just it's just a very dead place
that's why it's so feminine it's like
yeah the virtue signalers today are all
kind of vulgar spinners
every one of them is a vulgar species
today it's just like yeah ecology is
vulgar spinacism
everything is oneness vulgar he said
vulgar spin doesn't make new age
essentially it's vulgar spinosa
the way hegel reacted is that this is
just dead philosophy just fly it's too
easy that's not how things work
and then kant comes along and kant says
that phenomenological the nominal cannot
meet and they're separated meaning
there is a separation in the world that
spinoza hasn't acknowledged
okay there's a problem after count with
spinoza
the copernican internal count makes me
says there's a massive problem with
spinosa
you either go back to prior to count and
you dig into that and you dwell in that
and
the lures tried to do and failed or you
actually do what happened
and said that what if we haven't really
thought kant all the way through
properly and arrived at a monism that is
process
it's not a dead space it's process it's
thriving and it's alive and it's
dialectical it's moving all the time
that's what hegel does when he moves
into transcendental idealism
but it moves away from the controversial
by saying that no
actually the nominal is completely it's
not even interesting
just get rid of the numeral altogether
we obviously collide with
rocks all the time it's it's a given but
we live in a world of phenomena and the
phenomenology of spirit essentially how
the spirit
how does human spirit deal with the
phenomenology we're approaching
oh it has done that in different ways
throughout history hey
paradigms hey historicism hey
historicity and you know and i'm totally
with hegel and all these things
we work we're living in a very
historical world with events
and these events change history forever
and the question
now as always is will the anuject rise
in create tyrant with tarot or can we
avoid that
with still learning the lesson we should
learn from lynch mobs
learn the lesson let them kill each
other for god's sake and then
see the higher project rise which is the
force for constructive change of the
world
our project high project at the same
high project okay
high project we agreed on the high
projector last time it's a good term
because super deck and whitehead is
different although they're related
because the white head and super deck is
really the beginning of the high project
but the higher projected super data goes
out and acts in the world and does the
right things which is of course
stopping the lynch mode that's the first
thing you do then
providing forgiveness so you can try
again second thing you do
you can then add to that list or what
the high projective force does
to create a better more constructive
world
then i think we're on the right path
so uh yeah i i agree i'm with them i'm
with them that i loved spinoza when i
was younger
i struggled with kant it was a bit
boring but i realized there's no
movement to spinoza's philosophy yes the
same problem that i found with taoism in
china
you said you got yin and yang he said
but it has to be third force and people
tell you well it's the border between
you near
uh that's just a border this isn't
really happening there it's not a force
it doesn't put the thing on the move it
doesn't make it move it's not a problem
just
doesn't explain what you need to be
processed
that that's what taoism lacks and that's
why it opens up the door there must be
something else in china's culture you
can't just say with daoism
because it becomes banal
it has to be third force involved and
that is the hegelian dialectics
it starts with negation most abstraction
abstraction leads to concretion
the concretion then becomes the negation
meaning
what is the congregation not itself what
is it in the conclusion that is not
fulfilled because there's no perfection
anywhere in hegel's philosophy
what integration is not what is the
concretion
is it that it's not concrete enough for
the concretion to be concrete
that kickstarts the next negation makes
dialectical process
and then he moves so she she's argument
this is even valid for physics i think
he's a very risky territory when he says
that
but i think it's certainly valid for
human society in the human mind
and i'm perfectly happy with that that's
the only emergence factor where it's
needed
i have no idea but it sounds like it
sounds like
buddhism a bit to me that sounds very
vague
oh it sounds big to thomas once you look
into it that's how you become breathing
always sounds very vague to me like well
what does this actually mean that's why
i like whitehead you know it's also
complicated but you know you can really
dig into the hair is kind of a bit
but it might it's me i mean i haven't
studied hegel
i mean i'm kind of i would say if you
don't the other way you would say the
same thing
so hegel and whitehead are on a par i
said you do the metaphysics with the two
of them
and i think it's still where white it
isn't accomplished this amazing project
you can still use hegel to think it
through properly why said he's
incredibly
of course he's incredibly again no we
discussed that it's true bradley right
so so yeah
i'm sure that uh i mean i'm very it's
it's
it's i'll put it on my to-do list again
you know like and not the bad hegel that
the french read after the 1940s because
they misunderstood it completely when
the loss attacks hillary hasn't even
studied higgled properly doesn't get it
that's exactly what ends up in the wrong
place
and i think this is the problem with
contemporary spinal system
is that it doesn't start hegel carefully
enough to understand that hegel's
critique
higgen loved spinosa he called spinoza
the messiah philosophy
but he then looked at what spinoza was
missing and that's when he started
moving and that's what that is why
western process philosophy starts and
ends with hegel
and it includes whitehead
processing event these are the guys we
need
we can work on these four guys and then
we can go back and study and restart the
east again and again again
probably find similar patterns way older
as well
so here you go whitehead gerard yes
all right i'm on board well tell our
students
you got to get these guys eventually
it's going to be hard you know
long journey uh maybe don't jump into
hegel's signs of logic the first thing
you do
uh because that's like an incredible
challenge right
but once you do and you get it you
understand how he thinks and he really
thinks he's completely misunderstood
because it's very drought but then you
get it so that white it
once you to begin with get the
vocabulary just
don't think you understand the words by
themselves because they use these
words that you've heard before in a
completely different way than what you
thought they would
you have to read learn language itself
to study these masters
yeah but it's always deep thinkers
always need to redefine
part at least parts of language because
i think nietzsche richard why is it in
that way but hegel and white because
they're moving to the world of
metaphysics which is incredibly complex
metaphysics of phenomenology that's
where they're located
whereas with nietzsche and and girard
we're in the social
philosophy of the social this is social
flow this is understanding ourselves our
own predicaments who we are
and where we're at in society today it's
existentialism that's why they don't
need to invent a whole new vocabulary
because it's already there whereas the
other guys do
so is that what you're saying come again
andrew i didn't get
oh nichi and and um
and girard use the english language
right as we know it right they're
readable you know kind of readable
my nietzsche wrote so they're not
inventing a whole new vocabulary to
describe a whole new territory which
these other guys need to do somehow
well i'm always very very uh suspicious
when i
encounter um jargon and very complicated
texts
um you should be because in 99 percent
of the cases [ __ ] but one percent of
the cases most brilliant takes ever read
yeah that's why i i mean it's like
taking ketamine nine
nine ideas out of ten you get on
ketamine or rubbish but the 10th idea is
probably brilliant enough to be looked
at
so you know it's just it's just it's one
of those things yeah but just because of
almost all of it is [ __ ] it doesn't mean
there's gold in there but there is gold
in there and
actually when you get it you get it from
white when you get it just like
yeah could you have done it any other
way probably not
because you as a philosopher you sit
there all the time are you going to
invent new terms like an object and
higher project
yes we have to because we sat and have
these conversations
wonderful conversations with you and we
realized that
this voice coming from inside the
lunchbox doesn't really have a name
in a western language and objects
like in abject subject would make sense
anno meaning anonymous here
is like oh it's the voice that nobody
subscribes it nobody says they're that
voice but they all
claim the part of the voice and they
blame their own shortcomings on that
voice so this is
frick little voice that just with the
costume on it and you know it becomes
the tyrant
and when you realize that then you can
just go what's the inversion of that oh
god of course that's the savior figure
like the social
he who stands up to the lynch mob and
stops it or even goes to the cross in
case that's needed
okay that's essential the messiah who's
he
project so it's the very best in us
the most courageous in us the most truth
seeking in us the most heroic and all
that the best we can possibly be
the optimization of our own selves
ethically speaking
if we use with some luck and with some
hard work can get to that point
we have hyper objected ourselves we've
gone from super deck to high project
and the high project can both be role
model and it can be the same
oh that's interesting it's sort of like
the archetype but
but something new the ultimate hero
but that's the niche in overman yes and
that stands up against the hurt
and that goes beyond the hurt thinking
yes and that's what we agreed last time
that the sausage and disruptionism the
moshiach in judaism the savior and
christianity and the over many
nietzsche actually are the same figure
and it says that this is the guy stands
up to the mediocrity
of the lynch mob the banality of the
lynch mob and say
humans can do better at least i can do
better and i will show you how you do
better and if you only mimic me it would
be better than this [ __ ]
trash i got in front of me you know
that's essentially what the over man
says
right it was even mark's dream of the
proletariat and if you got to save
anything in marx and i think we should
we should re-read him correctly this
time and and
it helps we can throw marks at the wall
the proletariat
they hate they woke people hate parks
because they never read him and do no
idea
because he was a rock but he would hate
the walk people he would have hated him
uh but but with marx is the proletariat
and the proletariat is he loves the
capitalists and said
we could probably do better than that
this would not be the end of history
like we do for example with synthesis
and we say
why would atheism be the last of all of
this it's probably just a little blip in
history
it's not even properly thought through
it oh okay we take god from the past and
say it's not a creator god who's bored
on the cloud we just put god in the
future today what do you say now and
they says go oops you're not allowed to
do that and we say why not
and then we exposed them they hadn't
even thought of it they hadn't thought
of the hegelian negation again they
haven't thought it
you could just take the god word and
think of it
what is it all about and that's what we
can credit put it somewhere
if it does not exist yet
throw it into the future what happens oh
my god religion is back
that's a typical hegelian term see if we
could do that whitehead
i'm going to talk to brady ellen
tomorrow our genius our co-opening
genius
yeah how much is it my shared adoption
yeah uh i'm very much looking forward to
your podcast
yes yes yes and please do write it
without us we want to hear to you talk
about why didn't put in the parallax
yeah we're gonna do it on this book
because
i want to understand uh whiteheads
metaphysics from the point of view of
quantum mechanics
brilliant because then you can be very
precise what are eternal objects what's
concretia and what is the superject and
and because whitehead wrote his
metaphysics such that it's compatible
with both
relativity theory and quantum mechanics
and uh
and so rather than just reading his
words
so this book is basically about about
how quantum mechanics fits into a white
hedian framework
and it's it's not deepak chopra right it
is uh it's pretty
it's pretty solid so i think that's
going to make the the metaphysics of
whitehead extremely precise
up to uh up to mathematical detail so
that's that's what we're up to
fantastic and by the way we should add
that without watching there wouldn't be
quantum mechanics the way we understand
it max bohr wouldn't have thought the
way he did
whiter was ahead of them he wrote about
this in 1925.
yeah i don't know how how much he wrote
definitely about
uh relativity theory he had his own
theory
um and uh but i don't know
how much influence he had on physics
white hat i mean he was
definitely very important for
mathematics right i think that book
should solve that issue because it's
also historical books so it's probably
deals with black it's relationship with
the quantum mechanics quantum physicist
there are the the the thesis of the
1920s and white were obviously burton
russell and
and white was one of the worst leading
mathematicians i mean priscilla
mathematica made him
a massive academic figure in america so
there's always a connection
i think that book i haven't read the
book the book probably solves the issue
what was the actual relationship and how
did they relate to each other and learn
from each other inspire each other
this is the 1920s this is the golden age
of quantum mechanics yeah so wider was
in the middle of it but he also operated
he had left mathematics essentially and
moved into philosophy and theology
that's what he was interested in and
that's what makes him stand out makes
him jealous a unique
philosopher right all the others like
heinrich and and
what have you i mean they were not
mathematicians or or they didn't
understand physics so this is one of the
only great philosophers who was also
also brilliant physicist and a brilliant
mathematician that's of course why i
like whitehead
yeah he he was a leibniz of the 20th
century
yeah he stayed this is the liveness of
the 20th century yeah
right yeah i'd love to hear that love to
dig into a conversation that's going to
be the one podcast i really want to hear
this fall
well let's see where it goes it's
ambitious
it is very ambitious yeah okay and i
will credit you for it if i write about
it someday you call it there you go
it's part of the overall product which
is transcendental emergentism
sorry what do you eat for breakfast
alexander like
here hey gold for breakfast
i i read hegel before i open my email
box and get depressed
yes um i love books i love books more
than anything in the world and i love my
family i love the people i live with and
i love my books
i'm agoraphobic i hate people except for
you guys
why save them it's just like why even
bother it's just like
i'm pro-intelligence i'm not pro-life
and i'm pro-transcendence maybe that is
what life is in a way but
yeah that's that's
that's a good way to end i think yeah i
think such
final statement sexuality is the one
forgiving quality about humanity
it can't be [ __ ] thank goodness for
that
yeah all right good all right wonderful
conversation
good luck with the eddies wonderful
wonderful sweet sweet sweet andrew
you're left with the hard work of
editing this [ __ ] afterwards we do a
brilliant job at it
yeah no and i love the roughness of it
i'm so proud of being part of this